Guide to the James H. Laue papers, 1936-1999
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
James H. Laue papers
1936-1999, bulk 1960-1993
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
James H. Laue
C0055
43 linear ft.; 100 boxes
This collection contains the working papers of James H. Laue, former professor of conflict resolution at George Mason University. Materials include manuscripts, correspondence, diaries, legal documents, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Mariann Laue Baker in 1999.
Biographical Information
James H. Laue was born in River Falls, Wisconsin, in 1937. Laue graduated from high school in 1955 and went to college in his home town at the University of Wisconsin-River Falls, where he took a major in sociology. After earning his Bachelor's degree in 1959, Laue was admitted to the Harvard graduate program in sociology with a Danforth Fellowship, where he studied race relations and the sociology of religion under such distinguished sociologists as Talcott Parsons, Gordon Allport, and David Riesman.
During his graduate studies, Laue became involved in the Civil Rights movement, attending lunch counter sit-ins, church "kneel-ins," and protests organized by the Southern Christian Leadership Conference and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee. Laue's 1966 doctoral dissertation, "Direct Action and Desegregation: Toward a Theory of the Rationalization of Protest," grew out of a combination of diligent sociological analysis and first-hand experience in the Civil Rights movement. These experiences, along with a pious adherence to the core tenets of Christianity, influenced Laue's approach to conflict analysis, which he described in his 1976 University of Missouri tenure application as "a conscious and explicit linking of scholarship and action."
Combining social theory and practical problem-solving into a new practice of clinical sociology, Laue helped to establish the field of conflict resolution as a distinct academic discipline, and his career reflects both the academic and the activist sides of the field. From 1965-1969, Laue served on the US Department of Justice's Community Relations Service (CRS), an agency established under the 1964 Civil Rights Act to help resolve racial conflicts. After leaving the CRS, Laue held academic positions at the Laboratory of Community Psychiatry at Harvard Medical School (1969-1971), Washington University-St. Louis (1971-1974), the University of Missouri-St. Louis (1975-1986), and finally, George Mason University (1986-1993) where he became the first Lynch Professor of Conflict Resolution. Laue also served as President and Executive Director of the Conflict Clinic, Inc., a non-profit dispute-resolution organization, from 1984 - ca. 1989.
In 1976 Laue co-founded and chaired the National Peace Academy Campaign (N-PAC), which sought to establish a national institute for peace research and education. Three years later, President Jimmy Carter appointed Laue Chair of the congressional Commission on Proposals for the National Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution. The evidence gathered by the Commission at public hearings across the US, along with Laue's testimony before Congress in the early 1980s, was instrumental in establishing the US Institute of Peace and its funding counterpart, the National Peace Institute Foundation, which Laue also chaired during the 1980s.
Throughout his long and prodigious career, Laue participated in dozens of academic conferences, taught numerous classes and workshops on dispute resolution, published scores of academic papers, collaborated with Civil Rights activists and arms-control advocacy groups, delivered sermons at churches and speeches at graduate commencements, and remained active in the field of peacemaking and conflict resolution until his death in 1993.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the working papers of James H. Laue, former professor of conflict resolution at George Mason University. The papers document Laue's development as a sociology student and Civil Rights activist in the early 1960s through his career as a mediator and professor of urban sociology and conflict resolution into the early 1990s. Materials in the collection include manuscripts, correspondence, workshop papers, notebooks, legal documents, photographs, audio cassettes, and memorabilia.
Series 1, Correspondence, contains correspondence between Laue and his colleagues, including Civil Rights advocates during the 1960s and Peace Academy Commission members during the late 1970s and early 80s. The series is divided into two subseries of correspondence, the first arranged by date and the second arranged alphabetically by surname.
Series 2, Conflict Resolution Papers, contains materials from various conflict resolution organizations, initiatives, and workshops in which Laue participated as a leader or active member. The series includes mediation workshop materials, manuscript drafts of books and essays on the practice of conflict resolution, and papers documenting Laue's role in mediating such conflicts as the farm debt crisis of the mid 1980s, the Fort Worth I-30 expansion dispute, and the public memory of the 1970 Kent State shootings. Figuring prominently in the series is Laue's work with the Community Crisis Intervention Center at Washington University-St. Louis in the 1970s and the Conflict Clinic, Inc. at the University of Missouri-St. Louis in the 1980s (and later at George Mason University).
Series 3, Peace Academy Campaign Papers, documents Laue's leading role in the campaign to establish a U.S. Academy of Peace and Conflict Resolution. The series includes public hearings conducted by the Commission on Proposals for the National Academy of Peace, which Laue chaired in 1978-1980; Congressional records and hearings regarding the establishment of the U.S. Academy of Peace; newsletters, brochures, and meeting minutes of the National Peace Academy Campaign (N-PAC), which Laue co-founded in 1976; and various administrative, financial, and promotional materials from the National Peace Academy Foundation / National Peace Institute Foundation (NPAF/NPIF), and the U.S. Academy of Peace / U.S. Institute of Peace (USAP/USIP).
Series 4, Civil Rights Papers, documents Laue's involvement in the Civil Rights movement during the 1960s. The series is divided into two subseries. Subseries 4.1, Direct Action and Desegregation, covers Laue's activism in the Civil Rights movement during the early 1960s and includes notes, interviews, and other materials used in his dissertation, Direct Action and Desegregation, 1960-1962 as well as later essays on Civil Rights by Laue and others. This subseries also contains memoranda, pamphlets, and newsletters from such prominent Sixties grass-roots organizations as the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC), Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), the Southern Regional Council (SRC), and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Subseries 4.2, Community Relations Service (CRS), documents Laue's work for the CRS under the U.S. Department of Justice in the mid to late 1960s, where he became the head of Program Evaluation and Development. Materials include reports, meeting minutes, correspondence, personnel files, and speeches.
Series 5, Academic Papers, contains materials from Laue's work as a student, scholar, and teacher. The series is divided into two subseries. Subseries 5.1, Student Papers, covers Laue's academic career from childhood in River Falls, Wisconsin through college and graduate school at Harvard. The subseries contains sociology papers Laue wrote as a student, college notebooks, course materials, church sermons, and correspondence with professors. Subseries 5.2, Professional Papers, covers Laue's academic career as a researcher at the Harvard Medical School Laboratory of Community Psychiatry, as a professor of sociology and urban studies at Washington University-St. Louis and the University of Missouri-St. Louis in the 1970s and 80s, and as a professor of Conflict Resolution at George Mason University in the late 80s and early 90s. The subseries contains journal articles and commencement speeches written by Laue, course materials, academic exercises used in workshops on conflict mediation, and biographical materials prepared for annual reviews and tenure application.
Series 6, Conferences and Workshops, contains programs, presentations, notes, and correspondence pertaining to various conferences and workshops Laue attended or administered. The folder dates in this series generally refer to the dates the conferences were held and may not encompass the date range of all materials in the folder. Ranging from small local workshops to large international meetings, the conferences cover a range of themes including desegregation, clinical sociology, community conflict intervention, international arbitration, and peace education. Series 7, News Clippings and Articles, contains newspaper articles collected and assembled by Laue. Themes include desegregation and civil rights, international politics, biographical pieces and interviews with Laue, and the peace academy campaign. The series is divided into two subseries, the first arranged by date and the second arranged alphabetically by subject or newspaper title.
Series 7, News Clippings and Articles, contains newspaper articles collected and assembled by Laue. Themes include desegregation and civil rights, international politics, biographical pieces and interviews with Laue, and the peace academy campaign. The series is divided into two subseries, the first arranged by date and the second arranged alphabetically by subject or newspaper title.
Series 8, Photographs, contains mostly black-and-white photographs of Laue from youth through adulthood. The series contains several portraits as well as pictures of Laue with fellow students, family members, and colleagues.
Series 9, Memorabilia, contains certificates, drawings, posters, and other memorabilia mostly from Laue's youth. Included are several items from Laue's participation in the Wisconsin American Legion Badger Boys civic activism program as a child.
Series 10, Audio Cassettes, contains audio tape recordings of presentations, sermons, and speeches by James Laue, Jimmy Carter, and Martin Luther King, Jr.
Series 11, Oversize, contains newspapers and large format magazines mostly dealing with racial issues, protest, and civil rights.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1960-1993 (Box 1-3)
Series 2: Conflict Resolution Papers, 1967-1993 (Box 3-31)
Series 3: Peace Academy Campaign Papers, 1947-1990, bulk 1976-1990 (Box 31-50)
Series 4: Civil Rights Papers, 1956-1988, bulk 1960-1970 (Box 50-68)
Series 5: Academic Papers, 1947-1999 (Box 69-87)
Series 6: Conferences and Workshops, 1962-1992 (Box 87-93)
Series 7: News Clippings and Articles, 1936-1992 (Box 93-97)
Series 8: Photographs, 1942-1992 (Box 97-98)
Series 9: Memorabilia, 1949-1993 (Box 98)
Series 10: Audio Cassettes, 1968-1991 (Box 99)
Series 11: Oversize, 1960-1980 (Box 100)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds documents from the George Mason University Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution.
Index Terms
Persons:
Laue, James H.
Corporate Names:
George Mason University. Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution.; Conflict Clinic, Inc.; United States Institute of Peace.
Geographical Names:
Southern States--Race relations.
Subjects:
African Americans--Civil rights--History--20th century.; Civil rights demonstrations--Southern States--History--20th century.; Conflict management.
Document Types:
Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1960-1993
  This series contains correspondence between Laue and his colleagues, including Civil Rights advocates during the 1960s and Peace Academy Commission members during the late 1970s and early 80s. The series is divided into two subseries of correspondence, the first arranged chronologically and the second arranged alphabetically by surname.
  - Subseries 1.1: General Correspondence, Chronological, 1978-1993
    - General Correspondence - Important Letters on Race, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence [alphabetical, pt. 1], 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence [alphabetical, pt. 2], 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence re: N-PAC, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence re: N-PAC, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence re: N-PAC Commission and Gary NIS, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence - VUD, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1.2: Correspondence, Alphabetical, 1977-1988
    - A-C, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1979, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Conlan, Robert, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Executive Director of the National Peace Institute Foundation (NPIF)
    - D-G, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Gerber, Nachman M., 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Glickman, Dan, 1984, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Kansas Congressman
    - H, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Herrman, Margaret, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hogan, Harry, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Director of the National Peace Academy Foundation (NPAF)
    - J-K, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - King, Coretta Scott, February 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - King, Martin Luther to Morris Abram, September 28, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Letter to Morris Abram, President of the American Jewish Committee, re: SCLC position on Israel and Anti-Semitism
    - L-M, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Mapes, Milton C., 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Executive Director of the National Peace Academy Campaign (N-PAC)
    - Matsunaga, Sparks, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Hawaii Senator
    - N-R, 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Riesman, David, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - S, 1971-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Spencer, William, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Executive Director of N-PAC
    - T-Z, 1977-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Conflict Resolution Papers, 1967-1993
  This series contains materials from various conflict resolution organizations, initiatives, and workshops in which Laue participated as a leader or active member. The series includes mediation workshop materials, manuscript drafts of books and essays on the practice of conflict resolution, and papers documenting Laue's role in mediating such conflicts as the farm debt crisis of the mid 1980s, the Fort Worth I-30 expansion dispute, and the public memory of the 1970 Kent State shootings. Figuring prominently in the series is Laue's work with the Community Crisis Intervention Center at Washington University-St. Louis in the 1970s and the Conflict Clinic, Inc. at the University of Missouri-St. Louis in the 1980s (and later at George Mason University).
  - Adams, John P. - General, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Adams, John P. - Iran, February 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Adams' Police and Community Relations Project, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Appalachia: Case Study in Repression, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - An Approach to the Resolution of Disputes in Public Schools, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Arbitration Journal, March 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Arenas of Local Government Negotiating and Bargaining, ca. 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Article on Resolution of Community Disputes, by James Laue, May 30, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Asia-Pacific Organization for Mediation (APOM), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Asymmetric Conflicts: Approaches to Resolution", 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    by James Laue, Christopher Mitchell, and Peter Swanson
  - "Behavior of Third Parties: Roles, Rules and Ethics in Peacemaking and Conflict Resolution", January 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    by James Laue
  - Bhopal Incident [notes], December 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bishop Bennett J. Sims, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Atlanta, GA
  - Bob Reed, Current, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Building Forums for the Cooperative Resolution of Disputes in Communities", undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    by William Potapchuck, National Civic Review
  - Carlos Fuentes, April 16, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University, February 17, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University, February 17, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University - Conflict Resolution, Health and Tobacco, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University - Conflict Resolution, Schools and Tobacco, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Carter Center of Emory University - Tobacco and Health, 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Caux Scholars Program, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Center for Conflict Analysis and Resolution at George Mason University (GMU), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Institute for Advanced Study in the Integrated Sciences (ISAS) seminar; I-30 controversy
  - Center for Conflict Analysis and Resolution Newsletter and Report, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Center for Dialogue and Development - Board Meeting Minutes, October - November 1987 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Centers for Human Understanding - "Pavilion of Life" Project Meetings, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Centers for Human Understanding - "Pavilion of Life" Project Reports, August - September 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Centre for International Understanding, 1 of 5, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Centre for International Understanding, 2 of 5, 1977-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Centre for International Understanding, 3 of 5, 1981-1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Centre for International Understanding, 4 of 5, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Centre for International Understanding, 5 of 5, 1984-1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Child Custody and Divorce Mediation Articles, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Church Peace Mission - "Does Christian Commitment Make a Difference?", September - October 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Churches' Center for Theology and Public Policy, Shalom Paper Nos. 10-12 and 17, April and August 1981, May 1982, November 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "The Citizen Dispute Resolution Organizer's Handbook," edited by Paul Wahrhaftig, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Clinical Sociology Association Training Workshop on Intervening in Social Conflict (1 of 2), April 12-14, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Clinical Sociology Association Training Workshop on Intervening in Social Conflict (2 of 2), April 12-14, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Common Group Problems, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    pamphlet
  - Communication and Conflict Management Skills, ca. 1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Community Board Program Evaluation, December 1982-1987 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 1, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    outline with notes
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 2, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 3, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 4, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 5, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 6, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Chapter 7, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Forward, Preface / General Introductions, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Book - Working Materials to Be Assigned to Chapter Folders, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    contains correspondence between Bishop Frederick D. Wertz and John P. Adams re: textbook selection controversy in Kanawaha County
  - Community Crisis Intervention Center Discussion Draft, December 1974 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Center - List of Attendees at Washington, DC Conference, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Center Negotiations, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Community Crisis Intervention Center Newsletter - Crisis and Change, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Community Crisis Intervention: Issues and Perspectives" by James Laue, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    project proposal
  - Community Crisis Pamphlet Series - Evening the Odds through Training, ca. 1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    contributing writers: Martin Blum, Alana Cohen, Gerald Cormick, Frederick Hobby, Martha Kohn
  - Community Crisis Pamphlet Series - Preparing for Negotiations, ca. 1972 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Community Crisis Pamphlet Series - You're on Candid Camera, or, How to Organize Your Group with Videotape, ca. 1972 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Community Crisis Project, October 1, 1970 to September 30, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    report prepared by Alana S. Cohen, Director, assisted by James Laue
  - "Community Crisis Project - Report from a National Workshop on Community Crisis Intervention," April 21-23, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Community Disputes - Center for Mediation and Conflict Resolution (CMCR), 1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Board for Mediation of Community Disputes (BMCD) and CMCR Monitoring, 3rd Quarter Data
  - Conducting Foreign Relations through Building Political Relationships: Guidelines for Analyzing and Conducting International Relationships, March 31, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. and Clean Sites, Inc., 1985 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Background and Purpose, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Budget Plan, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Clinical Discussion, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    meetings on the Conflict Clinic and Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution at GMU
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Designing and Managing Citizen Involvement Processes, January 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Directory of Organizations Providing Dispute Resolution Services, ca. 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Discussion Paper on Scenaria for the Conflict Clinic, January 3-4, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Dispute Resolution Resources in the St. Louis Area, ca. 1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Draft Operating Plan, March 1, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Files, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Files, 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. Files, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Financial Status Report, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Introduction to Negotiation and Conflict Resolution, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    George Mason University
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Introduction to Negotiation and Conflict Resolution, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - J. P. Stoner, Rocky Mountain Mediation Team, March 1987 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Managing Ongoing Citizen Participation: A Workshop for Fairfax County Employees, June 14-16, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Negotiated Mediation in the Conflict Resolution Process, October 28, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Proposal to Expand the Work of the Conflict Clinic, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Conflict Clinic, Inc. - Proposed Agenda, Sept 20, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)